<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vanity, mischief and danger of continuing ceremonies in the worship of God humbly proposed to the present convocation / by P.M., a minister of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>P. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M68</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12350758</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12350758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 893:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vanity, mischief and danger of continuing ceremonies in the worship of God humbly proposed to the present convocation / by P.M., a minister of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>P. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Rich. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59983:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VANITY, <hi>Miſchief</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> Of Continuing CEREMONIES IN THE Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Humbly Propoſed to the <hi>Preſent Convocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>P. M.</hi> A Miniſter of the Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philip. 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let your Moderation be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Rich. Baldwin</hi> in the Great Old <hi>Baily,</hi> near the Black Bull. 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59983:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59983:2"/>
            <head>THE Publisher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THeſe Papers were ſent hither by a Reverend Divine of the
<hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that reſides in the Country. The Reader will eaſily perceive by the peruſal of 'em, that all our <hi>Clergy</hi> there, are not of the ſame mind with thoſe whom <hi>Vox Cleri</hi> repreſents. And had the ſeveral <hi>Dioceſes</hi> ſent us up
<hi>Proctors</hi> for the Clergy of the ſame <hi>Excellent Principles,</hi> and <hi>Healing Temper</hi> with this <hi>Author,</hi> to have ſeconded our Reverend <hi>Biſhops</hi> in thoſe good diſpoſitions to
<hi>Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which they ſeem to have brought with 'em, we might have had ſome better hopes of ſeeing an happy <hi>End</hi> put to thoſe ſad <hi>Diviſions</hi> which have ſo long <hi>ſullied</hi> the
<hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>weakned</hi> the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the
<hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> amongſt us. But yet we would not willingly deſpair of the <hi>Lower</hi> Houſe of <hi>Convocation.</hi> We know not but the opportunity <pb facs="tcp:59983:3"/>and leiſure which this ſhort Interval gives
'em for converſe, and calmer Thoughts, may do ſomething to allay their Heats, and mellow their Judgments, and ſweeten their Humour againſt the next <hi>Meeting.</hi> And the little peeviſhneſs, wherewith I doubt not ſome of the Clergy that continue diſaffected to the preſent Government, have leaven'd 'em, may ſoon wear off when they come to underſtand things better. But if notwithſtanding the fair Advantages put into our hands to lay the Foundation of a Laſting <hi>Union</hi> by reforming Abuſes, and removing the Obſtacles of it, if notwithſtanding all the weighty Arguments that ſhould at this time urge us to it, we are deaf to all ſeaſonable Counſels of Peace, what can we expect but that Almighty God will bring us into new Dangers, to cement our Affections, and ſend our <hi>Enemies</hi> to be our <hi>Peace-makers?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59983:3"/>
            <head>The Vanity, Miſchief and Danger of continuing Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in the Worſhip of God.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Reverend Clergy of the Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Reverend Fathers and Brethren;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the wonder and grief of all good Engliſh Proteſtants, that ſuch an unaccountable frenzy ſhould poſſeſs and hurry ſome hot Clergy men amongſt us, with a blind zeal againſt the good Propoſals of Peace prepared by the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners in the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Chamber. They make a tragical outcry as if the Church were to be undone, when there is no danger of parting with any thing but what may well be ſpared; nothing is intended but the removal of the brambles that have rent and torn her. Some do think that amongſt the inviſible inhabitants of the world there are ludicrous Spirits of an inferiour rank, and that theſe play the little tricks in diſturbed houſes. Some ſuch ludicrous Spirits act theſe men, who have a long time haunted and vexed the Church (the houſe of God) with the Pother they have made for <hi>Annis</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> and have made little reckoning of weightier matters. For trifles they labour all they can to heighten amongſt people an unſeaſonable and dangerous ſourneſs and peeviſhneſs. When a Popiſh Prince aſcended the Throne, they endeavoured to make us believe that we were happy, that <hi>James</hi> the Juſt never broke his word, and now they ſet all their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on work, to inflame people with animoſities and jealouſies of the Churches danger; when our gracious <hi>Joſiah</hi> labours to inlarge the intereſt, and to increaſe the beauty and glory of our Church. And this he doth in ſuch a method, as may expiate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſcarriages, and deliver us from the reproach of the late waſting perſecutions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He gives a Commiſſion to ſome of our Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Divines to prepare things for peace; then he calls a Convocation to conſider thoſe things, and recommend them to the Parliament. He puts it in our own power, in a great meaſure, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59983:4"/>to heal the great breaches, and repair the lamentable ruins and deſolations, that have been made by ſome amongſt us.</p>
            <p>To be a little more particular, becauſe this matter lays the greateſt difficulties in our way of Peace, and renders our preſent caſe moſt perplexed; Let all our Reverend, Pious and Learned Churchmen weigh well the manifold conſiderations that oblige them, by all means to endeavour, that the evil temper of ſome amongſt us may not prevail. I. The Honour of the Clergy is concerned. II. It is a vain thing to attempt the continuance of Ceremonies. III. It is unreaſonable. IV. The manifold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of impoſitions. V. Our danger preſent and future.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. The honour of the Clergy is concerned. Farewel to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and honour of the Clergy of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> if Ceremonies are now continued in the Worſhip of God. In the time of our affliction we did talk of Prayers and Tears, as the only weapons of Chriſtians; this will be lookt upon as hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical canting, if we labour to continue the inſtruments of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. We have promiſed to come to a temper towards Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; how infamous ſhall we be if we violate a promiſe ſo publickly given when under the rod? We have loſt many opportunities of Peace, we have now a Glorious opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and many engagements upon us to improve it.
<q rend="margQuotes">Shall an evil Spirit ſtill prevail among us to the defeating all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Providence,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,
<hi>pag. 12.</hi>
                  </note> and the croſſing of all attempts for Peace and Union? So that neither the errour that all men ſeemed to confeſs, nor the promiſes, which were then generally made, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our late diſtreſs, nor our preſent dangers, can bring us to a ſound mind, or to a calm temper,
<hi>that in this our day we may know the things that belong to our Peace.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>There have been condeſcenſions towards Papiſts, as in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany and the 28th Article; and ſhall we be ſtiff only towards thoſe of our own Communion, who have ſubſcribed the Doctrine of our Church? It will be thought that we bear a ſecret diſlike to pious Proteſtants, if we can yield to the enemies of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not to them. We ſhall load our ſelves with the crime of ingratitude towards Chriſt our Soveraign, and Diſſenters. We thank God for our Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, believing that he hath bought us with his blood; and ſhall we continue ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks to keep many pious Paſtors from feeding his Lambs <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59983:4"/>for whom he laid down his life? Our gracious Soveraign hath been indefatigable in his labours for our deliverance from Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Arbitrary power; he hath ſaved our Church and State, our Religion, Laws, Liberties, Eſtates and our lives; and how great will be our ingratitude and folly, if we continue obſtinate for the retaining thoſe things, that let in upon us the dangers from which we are ſo lately delivered, and do now hinder his Majeſties peaceable Government, and obſtruct his acting accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his glorious ambition, that deſigns chiefly the relief of the oppreſſed, and the advancement of the Proteſtant Intereſt at home and abroad? Let it not give offence, if I ſay that we ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful towards Diſſenters. They were ſteady for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the day of our diſtreſs, againſt the taking away of the Teſt and the Penal Laws by which they had ſmarted ſo much. There were more of our own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, than of theirs, that revolted from us and turned againſt the Laws. And now they have an Indulgence by Law, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the liberty of ſerving God according to their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and trouble not the Government with Petitions for more, neither have they given any indication of envying us the honours and Profits we enjoy. How ſhall we give an account to God and Man for all the evils that may be occaſioned by our obſtinacy? Mankind may juſtly abhor us, if we perverſly ſhake the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Peace and Happineſs of our Countrey for things of no value. The word Schiſm hath been a long time by ſome of us flung about at random; but now people will know on whom to charge it. The meetings of the Diſſenters are as legal as ours. None are by the Law of God or man obliged to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us upon the preſent terms. If we by continuing them drive people from us, the Schiſm will lodge at our doors, and we ſhall be the Schiſmaticks. They that for Rites labour to keep up our animoſities, juſtify the late violences,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, <hi>Pag. 27.</hi>
               </note> and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of all the Perſecutions of former times.
<q rend="margQuotes">Men may be ſtill Perſecutors, tho' they are not able to perſecute any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, according to our Saviours charging the guilt of intended ſins on thoſe who never acted them.</q> And God may charge upon them all the blood that hath been ſhed from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, from the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> unto the blood of thoſe glorious champions for our Religion and Laws, <hi>Eſſex, Ruſſel, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59983:5"/>Sidney, Corniſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you it ſhall be required of this Generation, Luk.</hi> 11.51. They who approved of and rejoiced in the murder of theſe men of honour, may have their hands full of blood in the ſight of God,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. It is a vain thing to attempt the continuance of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Wiſe men when they are earneſt in the proſecution of any affair, aim at ſome end that may recompence their diligence. Now it is exceeding difficult to find out what end people propoſe to themſelves in being zealous for the keeping up of theſe things. When a comprehenſion was endeavoured by that incomparable Triumvirate of our Church, the Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgman,</hi> the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> it was objected the conceſſions would tempt thoſe of our own Communion to forſake us and go over to the Church of
<hi>Rome.</hi> Whatever ſtrength there was in that Objection then, it ſignifies little now, Popery having appear'd ſince in its true colours. We need not fear the loſing of any, except them, who corrupted the Victuals, and put Garbage into the Veſſels of Beer for the Navy, who hindred the relief of <hi>Derry</hi> till many 1000s died for want, and are the cauſe that no more of <hi>Ireland</hi> is recovered, who by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold treachenies have obſtructed affairs of greateſt moment in <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Scotland.</hi> We may alſo loſe ſome of the <hi>Devil Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> club; it were better for us to be rid of them than to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by them in Proteſtant vizors. As for the debauches, if many or all of them depart from us, the loſs will not be ſo great as the miſchief they do us by pretending to be of our Communion.
<q rend="margQuotes">Let them declare themſelves Fanaticks, Papiſts, any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than members of the Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sharps</hi> Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>April 11. 1679.</hi>
                  </note> It would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be more deſireable to live in a mean, low, afflicted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without ſuch Company, than to govern the World with it.</q> There is great danger now of loſing multitudes to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters by the continuance of Ceremonies. Your coercive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is gone. I can heartily ſay with his Lordſhip Biſhop
<hi>Burnet;</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">God be thanked for it, that there is an end put to all Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in matters of Conſcience;<note place="margin">Exhort to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                  </note> and that the firſt and chief Right of Humane Nature of following the dictates of Conſcience in the ſervice of God, is ſecured to all men amongſt us; and that we are freed, I hope, for ever, of all the remnants of the worſt part of Popery that we had too long retained; I mean, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Perſecution.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59983:5"/>
            <p>The Act of Indulgence ſets all men at liberty, and it comes not long after a very fierce Perſecution, which will increaſe the number of Diſtenters more than ever. The barbarity of that Perſecution; the wickedneſs of the inſtruments, it being carried on by perjur'd Informers, and debauched Juries; the dangerous deſign of it, to fright the Diſſenters, or by Excommunication to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them from aſſiſting the ſober party of our Church in chooſing good Members of Parliament, and honeſt Officers in <hi>London</hi> and other Corporations, for the Preſervation of our Religion and Laws: theſe and other aggravations of that cruel ſtorm with the continuance of Ceremonies that then armed furies againſt us and our brethren, will breed a mighty prejudice in people againſt us, as a moſt odious and contemptible generation of men, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many miſeries and confuſions, we do for trifles, expoſe all the Intereſts of our Countrey into the greateſt dangers imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>We can impoſe theſe things upon none but the Miniſters and their Clarks. An unſeaſonable peeviſhneſs for them, will make many deteſt our fooliſh ſuperſtition, and forſake our Aſſemblies. There is no keeping up their honour, except we blind the people, which is now impoſſible. For if we neglect Preaching ſeriouſly, the Diſſenters will do it for us, and in 7 years their Preachers may be increaſed ten to one for what they are now. Our own Clergy who have a Zeal for the glory of God and the good of Souls, cannot avoid promoting the work. Many of them ſubmit not to Ceremonies out of choice, but as a burden from which they would gladly be delivered. If they did ſpeak out, it would be as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> did of wealth: <hi>non magis ambio opes quàm elumbis equus graves ſarcinas:</hi> They are to them but as the heavy load on the Carriers ſtaggering Horſe. As Knowledge increaſeth, Zeal for Ceremonies will grow more and more ridiculous.</p>
            <p>It is the hope of many good and learned men, that the time is at hand, when God will deliver his Church for ever from the darkneſs of the Kingdom of Antichriſt, and that the Nations will caſt away all things that have been inſtruments of advancing his tyranny and ſuperſtition. Surely that glorious day will open mens eyes. I have faith to believe that
<hi>England</hi> will not be blind, when other nations ſee.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling. <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 121.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">God will one day convince men that the Union of the Church lies more in the Unity of Faith and <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59983:6"/>Affection than in the Uniformity of doubtful Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is the condeſcenſion of the Government, that the deſired Union is propoſed to the Clergy, the Legiſlative Power may do it without us. The Lords, the Knights of the Shires and the Burgeſſes, know who are fit in their ſeveral Counties to be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of Peace, and Healers of our Breaches, and if we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be Peace-makers, they may (if they pleaſe) make a Law that the Members of both Houſes ſhall in their ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties chooſe three or four Divines to ſit in Convocation to offer unto them what may ſettle the peace of our Church. In the act of Indulgence, the King, Lords and Commons have acted like good Paſtors that are careful of the Flock<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I wiſh our Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion follow their good example. If we will not do our parts, we have no reaſon to think that the Nobles and Gentlemen will ſacrifice all their Intereſts to our fondneſs of continuing ſnares among the people. If a combuſtion ſhould happen we ſhall in the iſſue loſe more than is now deſired. A Ceremonial War hath been once fatal to Clergy-men; another will ſtrike home.</p>
            <p>The Church would loſe nothing tho all its Ceremonies were laid aſide. The beauty and excellency of it, is not at all advanc'd by a luggage of Impoſitions. They are no more an Ornament to the Church, than the Chains of a Galley or Priſon, are Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the poor man that is laden with them. The Church is the ſpouſe of Chriſt, her Glory conſiſts in a conformity to him her Head and Bridegroom, in holineſs and love; and not in ſuch geere,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 2.</note> as is common to the <hi>great Whore who hath made the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> of the earth drunk with the wine of her fornication.
<q rend="margQuotes">I dare affirm (ſaith Mr.
<hi>Bolde</hi>) that if the Rites and Ceremonies now in uſe in the Church of
<hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plea for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <hi>P. 11,
12.</hi>
                  </note> ſhould be altered, ſome changed, and ſome laid wholly aſide, by the ſame authority which did at firſt enjoyn them, the Church of <hi>England</hi> would ſtill be as impregnable a Bulwark againſt Popery, as now ſhe is. And I am fully ſatisfied there is no man will deny this, unleſs he be either a real Papiſt, or an ignorant ſuperſtitious fool.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After all the endeavours of our Bigots, neither theſe things nor they that labour to ſupport them will ever be valued by them that are ſeriouſly pious in our own Communion. All the art and power in the world cannot make trifles in the Worſhip <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59983:6"/>of God ſeem matters of importance to them that relliſh Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. What Trumpery are Habits, various Geſtures and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures to a man that is ſwallowed up in the contemplation of the infinite Majeſty of the Glorious God? or that is loſt in the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing admiration of his goodneſs and love? or that is ſunk into the loweſt abaſements and ſelf-abhorrence for his ſins? Such a ſoul may be loaded with human Inventions, but he can never look upon them as ornaments or helps unto devotion. On the contrary he may count himſelf mocked, and reckon thoſe impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fooleries no better than the fools caps and coats which Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors did put on the Saints of God, when they led them to the ſtake to be ſacrificed in the flames. They may be valued by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, dead Chriſtians; but the ſpiritually minded will look on them as toys fit only to adom Hypocrites.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> III. It is unreaſonable to continue Ceremonies. After all that the Wiſdom and Power of Impoſers can do, the judgments of men will differ. It is as poſſible to make their Hair all of one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, their Bodies of the ſame Proportion, their Faces all alike, as their Judgments to be the ſame in Rites and Ceremonies. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of obtaining Uniformity by Impoſitions, they break the Unity of the Spirit, and crumble the Church into Parties and Sects.
<q rend="margQuotes">Which may ſeem ſtrange (ſaith Dr.
<hi>Stillingfleet</hi>) the things that men can leaſt bear with one another in, are matters of Liberty;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iren.</hi> Pag. 38.</note> and thoſe things men have divided moſt upon, have been mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Uniformity; and wherein they have differed moſt have been pretended things of Indifferency.</q> Nothing but what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſhould be impoſed as Terms of Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">What poſſible reaſon can be given why ſuch things ſhould not be ſufficient for Communion with a Church which are ſufficient for Salvation?<note place="margin">Ib. Pref.
<hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and certainly thoſe things are ſufficient for that which are laid down as the neceſſary duties of Chriſtianity by our Lord and Saviour in his Word.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The practice of the Reformers of the Church from Popery is a good pattern for us to follow.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> Pag. 121. 122.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Such was the prudence and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the French Churches, in the compoſing their publick Forms of Brayer, that they were ſo far from inſerting any thing controverſial into them, that the Papiſts themſelves would uſe them, and inſerted them into their own Prayer book. The ſame temper was uſed by our Reformers in the compoſing our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59983:7"/>in reference to the Papiſts, to whom they had then an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial eye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And certainly thoſe holy men, who did ſeek by any means to draw in others, at ſuch a diſtance from their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as the Papiſts were, did never intend by what they did for that end, to exclude any tender conſciences from their Communion. That which they laid as a bait for them, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended by them as a hook for thoſe of their own profeſſion. But the ſame reaſon which at that time made them yield ſo far to them, would now have perſwaded them to alter and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thoſe things which yield matter of offence to any of the ſame profeſſion with themſelves. So far Dr. <hi>Still.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">By the letters,<note place="margin">Dr.
<hi>Eurnets</hi> Letters, <hi>Pag. 46.</hi> &amp;c.</note> (he means of our reformers to <hi>Bullinger</hi>) of which I read the Originals, it appears that the Biſhops preſerved the ancient Habits rather in compliance with the Queens inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than out of any liking they had to them; So far were they from liking them, that they plainly expreſt their diſlike of them.
<hi>Jewel</hi> in a Let. <hi>Feb.</hi> 8. 1566. wiſhes that the Veſtments toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the other remnants of Popery might be thrown both out of their Churches, and out of the minds of the people, and laments the Queens fixedneſs to them: So that ſhe would ſuffer no change to be made. And
<hi>Jan.</hi> 1566. <hi>Sands</hi> writes to the ſame purpoſe.
<hi>Contenditur de veſtibus Papiſticis utendis vel non utendis; dabit deus his quoque finem.</hi> Horn <hi>Jul.</hi> 16. 1565. writes of the Act concerning Habits with great regret, and expreſſes ſome hopes that it might be repealed, next Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if the Popiſh party did not hinder it, and he ſeems to ſtand in doubt whether he ſhould conform himſelf to it or not, upon which he deſires <hi>Bullingers</hi> advice. And in many letters wrote on the Subject it is aſſerted, that both
<hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to procure an Act for aboliſhing the Habits, <hi>&amp;c. Grindal Aug.</hi> 27. 1566. Writes that all the Biſhops who had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, had at their return dealt with the Queen to let the matter of the Habits fall: But ſhe was ſo prepoſſeſſed, that tho they had all endeavoured to divert her from proſecuting the matter, ſhe continued ſtill inflexible. This had made them reſolve to ſubmit to the Laws, and to wait for a fit opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe them. <hi>Cox</hi> in one of his Letters, laments the averſion that they found in the Parliament to all the propoſitions that were made for the reformation of abuſes.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59983:7"/>
            <p>It ſeems that theſe things were then eſtabliſhed by Parliament againſt the minds of the Clergy; they may now by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority be taken away, though ſome among us are againſt it, and care as little for the Peace and Proſperity of the Church, as the Harlot for the Child which ſhe would have divided alive. They are ſuch Paſtors, as ſhe was a Mother.</p>
            <p>The example of the Primitive Church will condemn our ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Indifferent things.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleets
<hi>Iren.</hi> Pag. 122. 68.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Certainly the Primitive Church that did not charge mens Faith with ſuch a load of Articles, as now in theſe latter Ages men are charged with, would much leſs bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den men with impoſing doubtful practices upon them as the Ground of Church Communion.<note place="margin">Ib. <hi>Pref.</hi> Pag. 10, 11.</note> There is nothing the Primitive Church deſerves greater imitation by us in, than that admirable temper, moderation and condeſcenſion which was uſed in it, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all the members of it. It was never thought worth the while to make any ſtanding Laws for Rites and Cuſtoms that had no other Original but Tradition, much leſs to ſuſpend men her Communion for not obſerving them. This admirable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the Primitive Church might be largely cleared from that liberty they allowed freely to Diſſenters from them in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Practice and Opinion: As might be cleared from <hi>Cyprian, Auſtin, Jerom,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Were there in the Primitive times many hundreds of men duly qualified for the Miniſtry,<note place="margin">Mr.
<hi>Gorber</hi> of Church.-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Pag. 49.</hi>
                  </note> kept out of the Church for their Nonconformity to ſome Opinions, Forms, and Ceremonies, of the truth or lawfulneſs whereof, the Diſſenters were wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, and which the Impoſers judged to be but things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indifferent?</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles did not at all favour the impoſing humour. The Holy Ghoſt and the Apoſtles were only for requiting neceſſary things:<note place="margin">Acts 15.28.</note> 
               <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us to lay upon you no greater him then than thoſe neceſſary things.</hi> How ſtrangely hath the Chriſtian. World been ſince altered? It hath ſeemed good to men to impoſe unneceſſary things as terms of Communion: But it doth now Here appear that this practice ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt. The whole courſe of Scripture is contrary hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <hi>Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
4.5.</note> This is not conſidered; for doubting conſciences are not at all relieved, they muſt conform or elſe be excluded from Communion with our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59983:8"/>Church in the Ordinances of Chriſt. <hi>No man put a ſtumbling-block or an accaſion to fall in his brothers way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom.
14.13.19.23.</note> 
               <hi>Follow after things which make for Peace and things wherewith one may edifie another. He that doubteth is damned.</hi> How little have Souls been valued by Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers? <hi>When ye ſin ſo againſt the brethren, and wound their weak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor.
8.12.</note> 
               <hi>ye ſin againſt Chriſt.</hi> Impoſers do not only wound the Conſciences of the weak, but they offend their head Ieſus Chriſt, who is alſo the Judge of the World and takes notice of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done to his flock.<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ye feed not the Flock. The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened, neither have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought again that which was driven away, neither have ye ſought that which was loſt; but with force and <hi>with cruelty have ye ruled them.</hi> Paul</hi> was a great Governour in the Church, yet he was ſo Far from uſing his Authority to the diſtreſs of conſcience; that rather than offend a weak brother,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.13.</note> he would abridge himſelf of his liberty as a private Chriſtian. <hi>Wherefore if meat make my Brother to offend, I will eat no fleſh while the World ſtandeth, leſt I make my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to offend.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> We have little reaſon to hope for this bleſſed temper amongſt us, while men <hi>ſeek them own, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> IV. The manifold miſchiefs of theſe impoſitions. No man can ſhew any good they have done, except it be good to maintain a corrupt party in Church and State, to the excluding a Pious, Sober, Peaceable, Diligent and Powerful Intereſt, that to a man would ſtand by the King, and venture all them concerns for him and the Proteſtant Religion, while ſome that have profaned the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for an Office, have by their manifold treacheries ſacrificed many hundred lives, and hugely hindred his Majeſties affairs. The Fabulous evils of <hi>Pandora</hi>'s box, come unſpeakably ſhort in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the real miſchiefs from Impoſitions.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleets <hi>Iren. Pref.</hi> 9.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy the main inlet of all the diſtractions, Confuſions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the Chriſtian World, hath been by adding other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Church Communion than Chriſt hath made.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If any man of common ſenſe will but open his eyes and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he may ſee plainly enough, that all the publick miſeries of mankind in Chriſtendom, from the exorbitances of Popes and the violences of Tyrants, owe their Original to the Spirit of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in matters of Worſhip. For if people were well inſtructed in the true knowledge of God and their Duty to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59983:8"/>and were not muffled in ignorance to maintain the Pride and Lazineſs of Churchmen, they would not ſo readily ſerve the Ambition of Princes, in invading the Rights of their Subjects at home; and laying waſte the Dominions of their Neighbours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. The miſchiefs I am ſpeaking of, are innumerable, ſome of them are reduceable to theſe ſix heads. I. Miſchiefs to the Church. II. To the State III. To Souls. IV. To Piety V. Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs in promoting a mighty increaſe of Prophaneneſs and all kind of wickedneſs. VI. Hindering a World of good.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. Miſchiefs to the Church. Zeal for mens devices begets in people a ſtrange levity of mind, makes them ſuch triflers in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that they diſregard the great intereſts of God and his Church in the World: They are not ſenſible, of the deſolations of Gods Churches in <hi>France, Orange, Piedmont,</hi> the Palatinate,
<hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> Of the judgments of God that threaten other Churches, of the plagues that may hang over our heads to chaſtiſe us for our crying abominations. What unthinking creatures are theſe? Yet they are good Sons of the Church, zealous for its<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ceremonies, not a pin muſt be pull'd out, tho innumerable tender Conſciences are wounded by them. They cry the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and are not mindful of the common danger from the Roman Gulf, that gapes to ſwallow down all. Such vanity of mind doth zeal for trifles infect men with.</p>
            <p>The zealots for theſe things, did ſo far labour againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our Religion, when the excluſion of a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor was endeavoured, that I have often heard good men ſay, that if Popery came in, it would enter at the Church door; God be praiſed, they were deceived, but it is no thanks to theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ſticklers, who brought the Church to the very brink of run, and now raiſe a clamour of its danger,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aion, <hi>Pag. 14.</hi>
               </note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">when every thing that has been endeavoured muſt prove its ſtrength as well as its glory; if we are ſo happy as to weigh all in even Ballances.</q> Churches will thrive better with the naked ſimplicity of the Goſpel, than the mock decency of Theatrical Ornaments, which are good for nothing but to maintain Formality, Diſſention, Pride and Tyranny. The glory of the Church conſiſts in a lively Faith, and ſincere love of the members of it; theſe are not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, but hindred by impoſing as Terms of Communion little
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59983:9"/>things, the lawfulneſs of which is doubted by many good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But when only neceſſaries are required, the Peace and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the faithful is not in great danger, tho ſome diſſent. For ſuch things will be more eaſily known and ſubmitted to by the greateſt number of ſincere Chriſtians.
<q rend="margQuotes">When neceſſary things are only injoyned,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. <hi>Pag.
74.</hi>
                  </note> their weight and truth will ſoon be known, and owned of all honeſt minds, or at leaſt are moſt likely ſo to be; and much ſooner and eaſier than the weight, and truth of little doubtful things; and by this means they would more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly move with joint conſent in one godly order, the matters of their difference being before hand taken out of the way.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Impoſitions do narrow and weaken the foundation of a Church. They are means of excluding multitudes of pious, peaceable and uſeful members from the Communion of it. The making of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary terms of Communion, which to doubting conſciences are unlawful, weakens the intereſt of true piety in the Church, by keeping out abundance of ſincere Chriſtians. A corrupt party may by this means be only taken into her boſom, and advanced to high power, all the reſt rejected, if not perſecuted. The late times gave us a deplorable inſtance hereof: for tho there was a ſober party in the Church, yet it could do nothing againſt a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Faction that had gotten all under foot; Firſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, then the ſober Conformiſts, laboured under a load of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and miſrepreſentations, as diſaffected to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All being graſpt by ſuch hands, the iſſue was like to be the ruine of Chriſtianity among us, if God had not been merciful to the Church in ſo great a danger. The intereſt of a Church ſhould be as large and wide as is conſiſtent with the terms of the Goſpel: None that profeſs Chriſtianity, and live unblameably ſhould be excluded.</p>
            <p>The Scripture is our only guide of Unity: Uniformity is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and confuſion, when men appoint other terms of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Service, and Church Communion, than are preſcribed in Gods Word. The impoſers are guilty of the Rents and Schiſms cauſed by ſuch Impoſitions.
<q rend="margQuotes">Where inventions falſe or uſeleſs are made the neceſſary Symbols of Religion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corbets</hi> Kingdom of God. <hi>Pag. 88.</hi>
                  </note> there a Sectarian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt bears Sway, and the gaining of the Secular Power will not wipe off the blot of ſuch a party. The name of Sectary may fit proud Uſurpers as well as blind Zealots.</q> The removal of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59983:9"/>may be a means to extinguiſh Schiſm, and to prevent it for ever, or at leaſt to free the Fathers of the Church from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of it.
<q rend="margQuotes">To load our publick Forms,<note place="margin">Hales of Schiſm. <hi>Pag. 8.</hi>
                  </note> with private fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies upon which we differ, is the moſt Soveraign way to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate Schiſm to the worlds end. Prayer, Confeſſion, thankſgiving, reading of the Scriptures in the plaineſt and ſimpleſt manner were matter enough to furniſh out a ſufficient Liturgy, tho no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either of private opinion, or of Church Pomp, of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or preſcribed Geſtures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did interpoſe it ſelf.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling-fleets
<hi>Iren.</hi> Pag. 122.</note> 'Were there a Spirit of mutual condeſcention (as in the Primitive Church) our breaches as to theſe things might be ſoon cloſed up, and the voice of Schiſm be heard amongſt us no more.</q>
            </p>
            <p>God, for the carnal ſtate of Chriſtians in the reformed Churches hath, let looſe the laſt and ſharpeſt Perſecution from Antichriſt upon them, by this ſevere Providence intending to deliver his Spiritual worſhippers from the Tyranny of Superſtitious Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, who by the deſolations of other Churches are admoniſhed to be wiſe, leſt they bring ſome great evil upon their own heads. Gods work ſhall go on, whatever difficulties lie in the way; it may be delayed, but it ſhall not be defeated. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had a forty years prorogation of their happineſs, the Rebels were all to die in the wilderneſs. The good things intended for the Church may be deferred till the removal of the carcaſes of the Sottiſh murmurers againſt our Royal <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the blind Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots who are unworthy to ſee the glory that is at hand. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhall no more plant the Tabernacles of his Pallace between the ſeas in the glorious holy Mountain. There may be very humbling diſappointments of the hopes of the faithful: God doth wiſely ſuffer theſe variations in the Church, for the tryal of his Servants, and to ſhew the neceſſity of the continual influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of his holy Spirit to raiſe and keep up our Souls above the animal life.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. Miſchiefs to the State. Zeal for Ceremonies begets in men a contempt of publick Rights and Boundaries. When they dote ſo much upon vanities in worſhip as to inſlave their Conſciences, and to deſpiſe their Chriſtian liberty, it is no wonder if they ſell at any rate their own and others civil Rights and Priviledges. I had rather forget than rake into the foul work ſuch men have made in Juries, Elections, Corporations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince the diſſolution <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59983:10"/>of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Parliament. Add hereunto the late violences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens Bodies and Eſtates by unreaſonable Proſecutions; Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Excommunicating, Impriſoning peaceable, diligent Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who deſired to live according to Gods Word, and did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the diſturbance of the Government. Yet many are ſo far bewitched into a fondneſs for theſe remainders of our former ſlavery, that they had rather ſacrifice all to Popery and Arbitrary Power, than quit a few trifles which for 130 years have been matters of contention and vexation in the Church, and do at this day ſhake the foundations of the Proteſtant Intereſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling. <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 123.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">It cannot but be looked on as a token of Gods ſevere diſpleaſure againſt us, if any tho unreaſonable Propoſals between us and the Papiſts, ſhould meet with ſuch entertainment among many, and yet any fair offers of union and accommodation among our ſelves be ſo coldly embraced and entertained.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the late times, when our Parliaments ſtruggled with Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power for the preſervation of our Religion and Laws, tho' the noble Peers ſpoke never ſo good reaſon in matters of the greateſt importance, yet two or three Biſhops always voted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. They were then called the dead weight. If it be ſaid, that they were over-awed by Soveraign Command; it is not ſo now. The hinderers of our happineſs (our preſent ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for Ceremonies) have all the encouragement in the World from the King, Lords and Commons. The eyes of the people are upon us expecting that we ſhould act like good Paſtors, heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the breaches and labouring in our ſtations to ſecure the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace. If we now diſappoint the juſt expectations of wiſe and good men of all ranks, we may neceſſitate the Government to take other meaſures for the preſervation of the Peace, and the ſatisfaction of an awakened people.</p>
            <p>The good temper, wiſdom, diligence, faithfulneſs and courage of Gods Servants have been uſeful to mankind. But a carnal Faction of Chriſtians being hurried by a mad zeal for little things, have oppreſſed theſe benefactors, ſtained the glory of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, beaten down the rents of lands, diſcouraged diligence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Trade, and brought the moſt illuſtrious Iſland in the World to a low ſtate. Nothing can recover a languiſhing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Corbet. <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> p.
123.</note> but the reviving of true Piety.
<q rend="margQuotes">Wherever it roots and ſpreads, it makes no ſmall part of the prudence, courage, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59983:10"/>and frugality, and by conſequence of the wealth and ſtrength of a Nation. There is no aggregation of men in the World wherein appears more of that which is good and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to men, than is found where the influence of this profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on becomes predominant, whether in a Nation or Kingdom, or City, or Family.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">The ſpirit of this profeſſion being ſober, ſolid and ſerious, is happy in diſpoſing towards the attainment of much perfection in all profitable ſcience,<note place="margin">pag. 145,</note> and eſpecially toward that which is moſt excellent and uſeful in humane affairs, to wit, ſolid and deep judgment. In this reſpect the children of true Wiſdom ſtand upon the vantage ground,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The continuance of Ceremonies may nurſe up a generation of Vipers to act over again the ſame cruelties, and to drive us back again into the miſeries and confuſions from which we are ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered. If God for our ſins ſhould give us up into their hands, they will make ſure work, and leave nothing to be done by thoſe that come after them. A relapſe in the ſtate, is as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as in the body natural.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> III. Miſchief to Souls. For trifles there hath been exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a mad tyranny over mens faculties. The Perſecutors would not ſuffer people to act like rational creatures: Tho in their conſciences they doubt of the lawfulneſs of mens devices in the Worſhip of God, yet they uſed all means to force them to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.
<q rend="margQuotes">It is the higheſt uſurpation to rob men of the Liberty of their judgments.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling.
<hi>Iren.</hi> page 118, 119.</note> A man hath not power over his own, much leſs can others have it. If every private perſon muſt judge what is lawful, and what not, which is commanded (as when all is ſaid, every man will be his own judge in this caſe, in things concerning his own welfare) then he is no further bound to obey than he judgeth the thing to be lawful which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What hindereth Governours from removing thoſe things, which they own to be in their own nature Indifferent? Is not the peace of weak Conſciences infinitely to be preferred before unneceſſary Impoſitions?
<hi>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the Poor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1.</note> Surely much more bleſſed are they, that compaſſionately conſider the burdens and oppreſſions of grieved ſouls. They that regard Conſcience in themſelves, will value the intereſts of Conſcience <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59983:11"/>in others. It is no commendation in Paſtors to imitate the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> Task-maſters, who
<hi>made the lives</hi> of Gods people <hi>bitter through hard bondage; all the ſervice wherein they made them ſerve was with rigour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.14.</note> The Miniſters of the Goſpel of peace, ſhould not be rigorous towards their people. <hi>Thou ſhalt not rule over him with rigour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 25.43.</note> 
               <hi>but ſhalt fear thy God.</hi> By the Antitheſis it appears, that where the fear of God is, there will not be in Paſtors ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and ſeverity towards their flocks for ſmall matters.</p>
            <p>Chriſt will have us ſhew our love to him in feeding his Lambs; this muſt be done with fitting food: impoſitions are Briers and Thorns; our fierce Bigots would ſtill teach their people, as <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi> did the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 8.</note> 
               <hi>with Briers and Thorns.</hi> This is much more eaſy to Loyterers than the drudgery of Preaching, which one called the Mechanical part of the Office of a Miniſter, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he would not much trouble himſelf with it. The neglect of this in many places, ſheweth, that there are more of his mind. What a zeal is there in many for ſhadows? And how are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls careleſly left by them at random, when they thus deſpiſe and neglect the Preaching of the Goſpel, which is the power of God unto Salvation?</p>
            <p>The little things impoſed are a means of depriving the Church of the ſervice of many uſeful Miniſters that are apt to teach, and would be glad to give the bread of life to thoſe Souls, that are by drones left in the broad way to deſtruction. The making un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary terms of Miniſterial ſervice which Chriſt never injoin'd, is an Invaſion of his Kingly Office. Some have been zealous for Prerogative when it was heavier than the loins of all the Kings ſince the conqueſt; but they make light of uſurping the Rights of the King of Kings. Chriſt commands his Miniſters to Preach, and qualifies them for that ſervice: No, ſay ſome, they ſhall not Preach, except they will wear the ſurplice. He bids them bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize: No, they ſhall not, if they will not ſign with the Croſs. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Woe is unto me if I Preach not the Goſpel, and Chriſt ſaith, Feed my Lambs: no, it is no matter, if you will not do it upon terms, deviſed by us. The want of theſe excluded Paſtors weakens the hands of thoſe pious Miniſters that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. The crying neceſſities of Souls will find work enough for us and them too; if every one of us had the zeal and abilities of the Apoſtle Paul. The humane meaſures for Miniſters may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59983:11"/>chance to admit ſome bad men into the Church; and is very likely to ſhut out abundance of able Paſtors, whoſe Conſciences doubt of the lawfulneſs of complying with terms not injoined by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of keeping out burning and ſhining lights, we had need trim ſome of our own, that give but a faint light, if any at all. We have ſome unſavoury Salt,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 13.</note> it concerns us to remove it to its due place, and admit that which hath too long been kept out of doors, to the great diſſervice of God and the Church. If we will not ſee ſome diſorders that are among us and reform them; the members of both Houſes of Parliament ſee them in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Counties, and there is hope that they will find a remedy. In the mean time the people ſee them, and there is in them ſuch a hunger after Gods Word, that in ſome dark neglected corners of the land, they go in great numbers to hear a Non-conformiſt, and are glad if he viſit them once a month. But above all God ſees what is amiſs amongſt us, and if we do not our duty, he will find a Beſom to cleanſe his houſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.24. Mal. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>and make them contemptible and baſe before all the People, that have been partial in his Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I have pleaded with a Reverend Divine in the behalf of excluded Miniſters, and endeavoured to repreſent to him ſome of the manifold miſchiefs to Souls by our rigour in impoſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary terms; I have been put off with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let all things be done decently.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> Will the violent wreſting that Text in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of mens Inventions, cover the guilt of deſtroying innumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Souls, one of which is worth more than the whole World, and their ruine may be for want of the labours of thoſe able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters whom we exclude for toys? Is the blood of Chriſt and of Souls ſo vile, as to be ſet to Sale for Stubble and Straw? Theſe things would be moſt contemptible, if we had the ſame value for Souls that Chriſt had, when he counted the whole World too light to be put in the ballance againſt one Soul,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.36.</note> and when he laid down his life to redeem us from the wrath to come. We may by our rigidneſs drive many from our Communion into the dark Sectarian paths, in which they may periſh: but how ſhall we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the miſchief that we have done? Tho we pour from our Eyes Rivers of Tears, or from our Veins Seas of Blood, we can never recover one loſt ſoul. <hi>The redemption of their Soul is precious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.8.</note> 
               <hi>and it ceaſeth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59983:12"/>
            <p n="4">IV. Miſchief's to Piety. The moſt learned Divines and the wiſeſt States-men in the World are but bunglers when they take upon them to add unto Gods Worſhip what he hath not appointed. Human Inſtitutions are but like clouts with which Chips are dreſt up into Babies for Children to play with. With theſe inventions Heathens and Atheiſts are habited like Chriſtians for the ſervice of the Devil, to corrupt and deſtroy true Chriſtianity. The World hath a long time groaned under them, it is high time for people to be Wiſe. Mankind hath for many Ages been poſſeſt and tormented with a furious Spirit, the Devil of Impoſition, it will never be well till this Spirit is caſt out. Piety may now as well live and flouriſh without our ceremonies, as it did mount without them above Idolatry, and conquered the World. It may be raiſed unto a new life from its decay, cauſed by a long and heavy oppreſſion under a load of humane Inventions. True Piety hath been hid in Corners; remove ſtumbling-blocks, and it will come forth and appear in publick with all its beauty and glory.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling. <hi>Iren.</hi> Pag. 121.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Allowing a liberty for matters of Indifferency, and bearing with the weak who cannot bear things which others account law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, we might indeed be reſtored to a primitive luſtre far ſooner, than by furbiſhing up ſome antiquated Ceremonies, which can derive their Pedegree no higher, than from ſome ancient Cuſtom and Tradition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Ceremonies in Worſhip corrupt peoples minds with vanity, make them light and trifling in the weighty concerns of God and their Souls.
<q rend="margQuotes">Pomp and Train of Ceremonies retained, will be apt to take up the heart of ſuch as are buſied in them,<note place="margin">Corbets <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> Pag. 103.</note> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the worſhip of God, and make it a dead work and carnal ſervice, and ſo the Spirit and Power of Godlineſs will decay and die amongſt people by this means.</q> Many think they have done much if they have exactly conformed to Rites and Ceremonies. Such are apt to forget the awe and dread they ſhould have in the Worſhip of the Divine Majeſty. They are ſo careful of outward Poſtures and Habits, that they mind not the bringing of their Souls unto God, in whoſe ſervice all the faculties ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged. What are all the inventions of men to our converſe with an infinite glorious Spirit? We cannot approach unto him but with our Spirits. The uſe of Ceremonies tends to the oppreſſion of the life and power of Chriſtianity. They are like painted win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59983:12"/>which may make a gaudy ſhew, but they much leſſen the light; or like Garments clog'd with Snow or Ice, they may load a man, but not warm him. The uſe of them waſts ſincere Piety. The preſſing of them is the cramming of Chriſtians with Stubble and Straw, and will ſooner choke than nouriſh true Piety and Charity.
<q rend="margQuotes">They when multiplyed, ſtrangely eat out the Heart, Heat, Life and Vigour of Chriſtianity.</q> The carnal part of the world is eaſily engaged for them againſt holineſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Scilling, <hi>Iren.</hi> Pag. 67.</note> and to ſuch a degree, that ſerious Piety hath been ſcorned and ſcoffed at, not only by the Mobile, but by higher ranks, not excepting the Tribe in the long robe, when engaged to be Advocates for Impoſitions; witneſs <hi>Samuel Oxons</hi> Books of Eccleſiaſt. Pol. and of Loyalty. The uſe of Ceremonies hath ſo blinded men that multitudes have been inraged with a mad ſpirit againſt the life of Religion. There hath been for a long time amongſt us, a bitter hatred of ſerious Chriſtians that endeavoured to be
<hi>pure in heart;</hi> ſuch have been reproached with the name of Puritans.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> Piety hath been ſcorned, vilified and perſecuted under the notion of Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">There is no doubt but this Church (tho its Government and conſtitution be ſo pure,<note place="margin">Mr.
<hi>Bolde</hi>'s Sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. <hi>Pag. 14.15.</hi>
                  </note> Juſtifiable and conſonant to Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Practice) would ſuffer very much, ſhould but the almoſt Ordinary Miſcarriages of a great number who pretend to the Clergy be expoſed to Publick View with an account of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement they meet with, or at leaſt how free they are from Threats and Moleſtations; while others who live better Lives, and are more conſtant and diligent Preachers, and do expreſs on all occaſions more of that charity and forbearance towards all men which Chriſtianity doth ſo much commend and enforce, are frowned upon, and left open to the rage and fury of beſotted, frantick and debauched Bigots.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">With ſuch as theſe if any man preſs for Regeneration,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> Sermons to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity on <hi>John 3.3. pag. 41.</hi>
                  </note> Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and a Holy Life, he was to paſs heretofore for a Puritan; then, for a Round-head; now, for a damn'd Fanatick: Nor ſhall he eſcape this cenſure, tho never ſo great a Church-man, and do exactly conform to the Church, as now by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; For 'tis Holineſs they hate more than Nonconformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59983:13"/>
            <p>The rage and cruelty of our furious Bigots, was lately grown bigger and taller than ever; they had quite trampled under foot the Diſſenters, and began a wild Cariere againſt Piety and Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in their own Body; they ſpared neither Nobles, nor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor Clergy: all good men in their communion had been ground to powder, if the aſcent of the late King to the Throne, had not put a ſtop to their madneſs. The Church may be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Piety by that ſtorm, but it is no thanks to thoſe furious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchees. When God lets looſe evil men upon his Flock, it is not to gratifie their ravenous luſt, but to make his ſheep love his fold, and keep to the paſtures which he appoints them. Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are Gods ſcullions to ſcour his veſſels of Honour for the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>The removal of Ceremonies will take away the vizour with which Formaliſts, Hypocrites, Wicked and Prophane men do cover themſelves. When Religion is ſtript of theſe things, and nothing injoyned but what is plainly commanded by God, they only will be counted Pious who live according to the Doctrine of the Goſpel: Drunkards, Swearers, Whoremongers and ſuch like will be known to be what they are, a meer herd of Bruits. The aim of Paſtors (it is hoped) will then be to promote a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual worſhip; that in all the duties of piety the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be engaged. The ſouls ſincere return and reſignation to God in every ſervice is the top-ſtone of holineſs. God being a Spirit, we cannot converſe with him but by our Spirits.
<q rend="margQuotes">To worſhip God in the ſpirit
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it is moſt agreeable to the nature of the Divine Majeſty,<note place="margin">Corbet's <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> Pag. 21.</note> which is worſhipped, and beſt fitted to glorifie him as God indeed; ſo it is alſo moſt efficacious to make the worſhippers more knowing in Religion, more holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly in Spirit and Converſation, and every way more perfect in things pertaining to life and Godlineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters will have ſomething elſe to do than to preach againſt Non-conformiſts: we may expect that their great deſign will then be to endeavour to promote the Glory of God, to convince men of a future ſtate, to advance holineſs, ſobriety, peace and uſeful diligence in the world. Theſe things will come home to the faculties of conſidering men, and they will think that their Teachers are in good earneſt, when they are Zealous for things wherein the intereſt of their own ſouls is concerned.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59983:13"/>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Patrick</hi> gives excellent advice to Minsſters in two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Divine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick</hi> pag. 72.
73.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I. Let us be much in private prayer. Our time is ſhort as well as other mens, and many times ſhorter, though our account be greater; therefore let us ſpend much time with God, as we endeavour to ſpend it all for him. Let not a croud of thoughts in our Studies, nor a croud of company, thruſt God away from our Souls, but let them frequently retire unto him as the fountain of all light and good. Prayer before our ſtudies is the Key to unlock the ſecrets of God, and prayer afterward is the turning of the Key to lock them ſafe into our hearts. Prayer ſharpens our appetite after truth; and when we have found it, it ſets an edge upon the truth, and makes it more cutting and penetrating into the heart. II Let us look to our ends in our work. Without this our labour would be in vain. Let us believe our ſelves what we ſpeak, and then we ſhould mind the Glory of God, and not our ſelves. Alas! what is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of men when we are gone, but like a ſound in a dead mans ear? And what is it when we are alive, but an empty breath that is loſt ſooner than got, and is got oftentimes by idleneſs ſooner than taking pains? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let the good of men therefore, and the Glory of God be the mark at which we aim: And the Lord in Heaven hear our Prayers, and bleſs our Preaching.</q> If all our Clergy by what Titles or Dignities ſoever diſtinguiſhed did truly follow this advice, there would be no Zealots among us for Impoſitions, the deſtroyers of Piety and Charity.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> V. Miſchiefs in promoting a mighty increaſe of prophaneneſs and all kind of wickedneſs. The Zealots for mens devices have little regarded what evils corrupted Church and State, if the honour of theſe toys was ſupported. They have been ſo mindful of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining theſe things, that by their neglect they have ſuffered (if not worſe) a flood of prophaneneſs and other wickedneſs to break in upon us.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. Prophaneneſs in the outragious contempt of holy things There is ſcarce any thing in Religion that hath eſcaped the ſcorn and reproach of blind Zealots: The Ordinance of Preaching, the Lords day, the Scripture, our Holy Religion, and Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; all have been ſtruck at.</p>
            <p>The Ordinance of Preaching. The conſtant, ſerious, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent performing of this, would ſpread knowledge amongſt the <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59983:14"/>people to the prejudice of human Impoſitions in Divine Worſhip. They would ſee what light things they are in the ſervice of God. Preaching hath therefore been ſtruck at under pretence of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting Prayer as the chief work of a Miniſter. Dr. <hi>Holdſworth</hi> takes notice of it, and on the contrary maintains at large this <hi>Theſis: Prae dicatio verbi Dei opus eſt &amp; ordine primum, &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me proprium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praelect. Theolog. in</hi> Mat. 13.52. Lect. 3. pag.
19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; longe praecipuum, inter omnia Curae Paſtoralis exercitia; ad quod ſua ſtudia &amp; animum, &amp; ſe totum, &amp; imprimis, &amp; maximè, &amp; ſaepiſſimè appellere debeat &amp;c.</hi> Yet ſome have been ſo fierce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt preaching Gods Word, that Lectures have been diligently ſuppreſſed. Prayers have been much advanced above Preaching as that which might be ſpared if the others were read. Let us hear another Dr. concerning this abuſe, and the Practice of the
<q rend="margQuotes">Church in the primitive times:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling. <hi>Iren.</hi> pag. 333.</note> Men that were imployed in the Church then, did not conſult for their Eaſe or Honour, and thought it not enough for them to ſit ſtill and bid others work, but they were of <hi>Pauls</hi> mind, <hi>neceſſity was laid upon them, yea, wo was unto them if they Preached not the Goſpel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor.
9.16,</note> Publick Prayers were not then looked on as the more Principal end of Chriſtian Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies than Preaching <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Were the Apoſtles Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt to go Pray, or Preach? and what is it wherein the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſucceed the Apoſtles? Is it in the office of Praying, or Preaching? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are Miniſters in their Ordination ſent forth to be readers of Publick Prayers, or to be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Gods Holy Word,<note place="margin">pag. 334.</note>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is one of the unhappy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences which follows mens judging of the ſervice of God, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Practices of the Church, when it came to enjoy eaſe and plenty, than by the ways and Practices of the firſt and pureſt Apoſtolical times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> People need as much inſtruction as ever, and ſo much the more in that they are apt to think now the name of Chriſtians will carry them to Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Men muſt be beat off from more things which they are apt to truſt to for Salvation now, than in thoſe times: men could not think ſo much then, that diligence in Publick Aſſemblies, and attendance at Publick Prayers, was the main Religion. Few would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſtianity in thoſe times, but ſuch as were reſolved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand rather to let go their lives than their Profeſſion: but the more Profeſs it now, without underſtanding the terms of Salvation by it;<note place="margin">pag. 335.</note> the greater neceſſity of Preaching to inſtruct men in it.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59983:14"/>
            <p>The Lords day hath met with many and great Enemies among the Ritualiſts. This is a gracious injunction and gift of infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, neceſſary for us to reſcue our Souls from Levity of mind, carnal affections and worldly cares, and to feed, nouriſh and ſtrengthen them with Spiritual Meditations and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Joys. They that ſeriouſly endeavour to converſe with God and their own Souls, know the truth hereof: But Formaliſts are ignorant of the Divine life, to them the Sabbath is a burden,<note place="margin">Amo. 8.5.</note> they ſay, <hi>When will it be gone?</hi> Pleading ſome years ſince with a grave Ceremonious Don of our Church for the ſanctifying of the Lords day, by ſpending it in Religious exerciſes, he was ſo far from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding me, that his return was, Shall a man be a whole day on the rack? Such a myſtery is the Spiritual life to a man that ſpends his Zeal on Rites and Ceremonies. To eaſe ſuch animal men from the rack, a book for ſports on the Lords day was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined Miniſters to read in the time of Divine Service. Here we may wonder at the Fantaſtical humour of a ſort of men, they perſecuted the people for working in their lawful callings on the Feſtival days; and ſilenced conſcientious Miniſters for not read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a book for ſports on Gods Day. It was pretended in that ſportful book, that the ſuperſtitious obſervation of the Lords day, did render his Majeſties Subjects unfit for his Service in the Wars. But what kind of Fighters thoſe ſportmongers on Gods day were, the event ſhewed not long after.<note place="margin">Jer.
44.21.</note> 
               <hi>Did not the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them, and came it not into his mind?</hi> The Lords day duly obſerved is a mighty inſtrument for the promoting the Life of Godlineſs in the Souls of Chriſtians. The ſerious obſervation of this begets in people another Spirit than is in Chriſtians of other Reformed Churches. They are much more above the carnal World, than moſt of them, and than any that ſlight that day in our own.</p>
            <p>The Scripture hath its ſhare of contempt from Ceremonialiſts; of the truth hereof the Impoſitions of <hi>Rome</hi> are a full proof. We need not go ſo far: For other Impoſers are guilty of the ſame in a lower degree, while they injoyn on: Miniſters and People terms of Communion not warranted by the Word of God. And this is the worſe, becauſe when Scripture is urged, fooliſh preciſeneſs and impertinency hath been charged on them, that have pleaded againſt ſuch unſcriptural Impoſitions.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59983:15"/>
            <p>Our holy Religion hath been mightily expoſed to the ſcorn of evil men, when they ſee pretenders to it ſpend all their zeal on little things.
<q rend="margQuotes">Force and Rigorous Impoſitions, make men ſuſpect the weight of the thing it ſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Stilling. <hi>Iren. Pref.</hi> pag. 11.</note> when ſuch force is uſed to make it enter.</q> When people are very earneſt for trifles, as if the whole weight of Religion depended on them, ſome may be tempted to ſuſpect that all is but a cheat, a trick of cunning Churchmen to form people to ſerve their purpoſes; eſpecially, when one that hath written books for Conformity ſhall ſay, that is the beſt Body of Divinity, that enables a man to keep a Coach and ſix Horſes.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt who hath ſuffered ſo much for ſinners, ſuffers again by the mockery of Ceremonies without the heart. All the pomp of them is to him a Crown of Thorns, if perſecutors for them wound the weak conſciences of his members. One may conform to the uſe of the tranſient ſign of the Croſs, and Scoff at the knowledge of Chriſt; a book ſo called,<note place="margin">Parker <hi>of Religion and Loyalty</hi> Par. I. Pag. 28, 29. Lon. 1684.</note> ridicules the Title it bears. Another is much more bold, takes upon him to dethrone the King of Kings, and ſet him at the footſtool of Crowned duſt.
<q rend="margQuotes">It is but a crude expreſſion (not to call it prophane, becauſe it is ſo common by cuſtomary miſtake) to affirm that Kings are Supream Governours under Chriſt. They are and ever were ſo under God, but ſo as to be Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to Chriſt, as Chriſt is head of his Church within their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. Miſchiefs in promoting an increaſe of all kind of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The moſt immoral men, if they did pretend zeal for Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and were furious againſt Diſſenters, did paſs for good Chriſtians, and true ſons of the Church. This falſe meaſure hath hardened abundance in their evil ways, mightily cheriſhed and increaſed vice in the Land. Conformity to Ceremonies hath been a Cloak that hath covered the moſt filthy abominations. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of them in the Worſhip of God will be a gratification of the worſt Chriſtians, and a grief to the beſt. A Ceremonious ſervice is apt to corrupt people with ſenſuality: It is eaſy to the fleſh, not croſſing any of its intereſts. Holineſs requires the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the thoughts and imaginations of the heart unto Chriſt, that we ſhould be pure in thought, word and deed. But a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial worſhip is only a bodily exerciſe, which tho it profiteth <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59983:15"/>little (as the Apoſtle ſaith) yet it ſerves to ſilence natural conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to repreſent men to impoſing Governours as good mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church. This is all that ſenſual men look for, and if they obtain this, they let looſe the reins to all exceſs of riot. How much did ſenſuality increaſe, when it was connived at (if not incouraged) and tender conſcience, as the only bug-bear, was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where hunted with a full cry? People are regardleſs of the power of Chriſtianity, when they find that their Superiors are contented with a conformity to the externals of it. The moſt vicious people cry, The Temple of the Lord, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to cover their Immoralities. Away then with theſe mighty Engines of miſchief: Let us all chiefly mind and purſue thoſe things which tend moſt to the promoting the work of Regeneration in the world. If this courſe be taken, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites
<q rend="margQuotes">will loſe their advantages of ſeeming religious by zeal for thoſe things wherein Religion doth not conſiſt,<note place="margin">Corbets <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> Pa. 74.</note> and carnal deſigns and intereſts that now rend the Churches, and trouble all things, would be defeated and abandoned. Of all things that ſhould moſt be regarded which qualifieth for heaven;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> that is holineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Without it there is no entring into that glorious Kingdom.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.5. Heb. 12.14.</note> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs not only prepares for eternal life, but is greatly advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Church in this World.
<q rend="margQuotes">Whereſoever it is, it invigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates others of this fellowſhip that are near it,<note place="margin">Ibid. Page
130.</note> and it commands awe and reverence from all-men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> VI. Hindring a world of good. It cannot be proved that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in Worſhip ever did any good. The inſtances abovemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned fully prove that they have been very Miſchievous; and there is this to provoke all good Chriſtians to deſire the caſting them away, they hinder a world of good. They hinder Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Love and Communion of Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. They hinder reformation. The Quarrels occaſioned by them hinder the Progreſs of the Reformed Religion. Biſhop
<hi>Burnet</hi> in relation to <hi>England</hi> chargeth this upon the
<q rend="margQuotes">long and fierce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts among us about things which we all confeſs are indifferent in their own nature.<note place="margin">Exhortati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, <hi>Pag. 13.</hi>
                  </note>
               </q> There may yet be expected a further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Churches to a higher degree of purity to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the power of Godlineſs. In the Reformation in the laſt Century the Pope was driven hence in ſuch haſte that he left
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59983:16"/>ſome of his toys behind him. Theſe have continued too long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, to the great diſturbance of the Church, and oppreſſion of ſerious Piety. God by the late advances of Popery among us, hath ſhewed us what it is, that both it, and all things that belong to it may be abhorred by us, and rejected with indignation. He herein deals with us as he did with the Iſraelites;<note place="margin">Mic. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt go even to</hi> Babylon, <hi>there ſhalt thou be delivered.</hi> They were delivered from <hi>Babylon</hi> the moſt potent Tyranny on Earth in thoſe times, and they were purged from Idolatry in <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Fountain and Nurſery of Idolatry then in the World. For they never revolted again to Images after their return from Captivity. But they were afterward guilty of our error, doting on humane Impoſitions, they ſet up Traditions by which they made void the Commandments of God. In the firſt Reformation we were cleanſed from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in the next I hope we ſhall go a ſtep further. The caſe of the Jews and <hi>Babylon</hi> may have a reſemblance to the Church and Spiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> now. The Church is prevailing, tho ſhe lately ſeemed to languiſh. Her ſtruglings under the renewed aſſaults of Antichriſt tend to her higher advancement. We have been in ſuch danger of deſtruction by Popery and Arbitrary Power, that our ruine ſeemed unavoidable. God hath wonderfully reſcued us from all the Plagues that ſeemed to hang over our heads: We ſhould therefore caſt off all thoſe things, that by wounding weak conſciences may have provoked him to ſet darkneſs in our paths, and by dividing us did help to bind us as ſlaves under the moſt cruel Tyranny. God may intend this reformation among us, by the glorious revolution he hath wrought, by our Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, by which the tide of the laſt perſecution from Antichriſt ſeems to be turned, and the Church to be upon the riſing ground. Let us then retain nothing that may hinder the good work of God among us.
<q rend="margQuotes">That perſecution (ſaith the Learned Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi>) which,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>on</hi> Pſal. 87.5. Pag. 27.</note> I ſuppoſe, remains yet to be acted, and which will be the ſmarteſt, ſhall be ſucceeded by the cleareſt eruption of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, wherein the Goſpel ſhall recover its Ancient and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Glory. If he doth ſuffer enemies to prevail, they ſhall be but as whisks to bruſh off the duſt,<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>on</hi> Exo. 15.9, 10. P.
52. Ibid. <hi>on</hi> Pſa. 87.5. P. 39.</note> wiſps of Straw to cleanſe the filthy pot. Before the <hi>Philadelphian</hi> State (which it is likely we are not far from) there will be a combat wherein the Church is to bear a ſignal Teſtimony to the truths of Chriſt in the way of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59983:16"/>conflict, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.5. The glorious State of the Church at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the witneſſes, ſhall be preceded by ſuch a calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as ſhall be the terrour of the Godly, and the triumph of an enemy devoted to a ſudden and unexpected deſtruction, <hi>Rev.</hi>
11.9, 10, 11, 12.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>His going forth is prepared as the morning,</hi> Hoſ. 6.3.<note place="margin">Vol. 2. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Pſal. 87.5. Pag. 31.</note> His appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for and in his Church, is as certain as the dawning of the morning light at the appointed hour: All the Clouds which threaten a perpetual night, cannot hinder it, all the workers of darkneſs cannot prevent it; this morning will dawn whether they will or no. There ſhall be a perpetuity in this Spiritual State;<note place="margin">Ib. Pag. 40.</note> only between the beginning and compleating it, <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall be let looſe: but for a little ſeaſon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3. And after this the Church ſhall not have one blow more from Hell; but the Devil muſt for ever give over nibbling at her heel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us not fight againſt God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act.
23.9.</note> All dividing terms of Communion or of the exerciſe of the Miniſtry, are the things to be removed in order to a more perfect reformation of the Church, and to make way for a more holy and bleſſed State of Piety and Love, which may be at hand, if by our perverſeneſs we do not put away this happineſs from us. God is doing this work in the world; it ſhall go on, tho we periſh by our fooliſh obſtinacy.<note place="margin">5.39.</note> 
               <hi>If it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it; leſt haply ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi> All wiſe and good men amongſt the Clergy and People, deſire the taking away the inſtruments of our confuſions. None at this time can have a zeal for theſe things, except ſuch, who either know not how to appear religious without a dreſs of trifles, or they have ſuch a ſecret reſerve for the late Kings Intereſt, that they had rather have an Army of <hi>French</hi> Dragoons,
<hi>Iriſh</hi> Cut-throats and barbarous Highlanders, in the bowels of this Kingdom, than ſee us ſtrengthened by an Univerſal affection to our gracious Soveraign, and United in Love and Charity one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Ceremonies have been the Clokes of Impiety and Miliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: If theſe are continued it will be exceeding difficult to purge out vice, which will ſhelter it ſelf under them. People are prone to be fond of their own Idols, there will be more regard had for conformity to them, than care of reformation. Tho our Pious Fathers are never ſo zealous againſt ſin, the Under-Officers will <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59983:17"/>indulge the Sons of <hi>Eli.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bold.</hi> Plea for moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pag. 41.</hi>
               </note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">A Regiſter, when told that a perſon preſented was one of us, he will ſwear and be drunk as well as the beſt of us; called the Church-Warden, and chid him very ſharply, telling him he was a moſt impudent and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous rake-hell, in that he durſt adventure to preſent ſo worthy a Gentleman as that was.</q> We are all apt to look on the faults of our own party with a favourable eye. Debauchery came in with Ceremonies, we ſhall be happy if they fall together. <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exalteth á Nation, but ſin is a reproach to any people,</hi> Prov.
14.34.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. They hinder love among the people, and between the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and their Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. Love amongſt the people is mightily hindred by the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and animoſities cauſed by human Impoſitions. If we look back on our miſerable confuſions, and well conſider how far our diviſions contributed toward the bringing us into them, we ſhall find that theſe Roman Nettles have not been leſs miſchievous to us, than the fiery Serpents were to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. They were the Rod of God, and directed them to the Brazen Serpent, a Type of him who was to be the healer of the Nations. Our Bigots are for continuing theſe tormentors amongſt us, but provide nothing to heal the wounds they make; they will not (as one ſaid) part with a rag to bind up the bleeding wounds of the Church. The Sons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> cry, The Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and do moſt endanger it by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring the preſervation of theſe tools of diſſention, hindring our joining together in the Service of God with one heart and one Soul, and uniting to defend the King and Kingdom againſt the common Enemy. Love is the bond of perfection, and would make us mighty againſt all that hate us, if theſe Incendiaries did not raiſe jealouſies of the Churches danger, it may be with a deſign to maintain a faction among us to make an after-game for the late King.</p>
            <p>If we review the method taken, the deſign of and the uſe that hath been made of the re-eſtabliſhment of Ceremonies, we ſhall plainly ſee the wild fire that is in the preſent zeal of our hot-ſpurs. Soon after the Reſtauration, the enemies of Piety, and Vertue reſolved to continue the diviſion between the two moſt potent Intereſts of the Proteſtants in <hi>England;</hi> to further this a ſham-plot was caſt upon the Presbyterians in ſeveral Counties; this was <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59983:17"/>ſo improved in Parliament that Penal Laws were eaſily obtained to inſlave and deſtroy the Diſſenters. And when thoſe Laws did not ſufficiently purge Pious Miniſters out of the Church, <hi>Clifford</hi> (a Papiſt) moved that they might be ſtab'd with an Oath, which ran like Wild fire amongſt the Penſioners, and ſo the renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Covenant was enacted into a Law, which turned out ſome that in their Judgments were for a Liturgy and Epiſcopal Government. The gaining of this point was of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the deſigns of the Popiſh Cabal, that the Parliaments could never obtain the removing of our differences by a Legal Indulgence. When the Parliament voted that the proſecution of Diſſenters was a grievance, and dangerous to the Kingdom, they were ſent home to hear a Libel read againſt them in the Churches and the fire of perſecution raged more than ever. The Court would never part with theſe bombs that were made to Sacrifice both parties to the rage of the Popiſh Conſpirators. Firſt, The Diſſenters were worried and waſted by the moſt violent Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, inflamed by the ſecret enemies of Religion, and promoted by debauched and perjured Informers. Then in the Church, the moſt Pious and Sober members of it were proſecuted as diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Government. The conſpirators who were againſt a Legal indulgence, could afford an Indulgence againſt Law, and that was never thought of, but when the Proteſtant Intereſt was to pay very dear for it. There were but two Declarations of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence: One, when the Dutch were to be rob'd of a vaſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their <hi>Smyrna</hi> Fleet, and a War to be made for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Proteſtant States of <hi>Holland;</hi> the other was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to choak the whole body of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, who for not reading it in their Churches were to be Sacrificed to
<hi>Moloch</hi> by <hi>Jefferies</hi> and his brethren of the Inquiſition. Our <hi>Bigots</hi> muſt have gone to pot with the reſt if God had not inſpired our Gracious Soveraign to expoſe himſelf between us and danger, and yet ſome of theſe men do murmur at the happineſs they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy by his goodneſs and courage.</p>
            <p>Now, if after we have been all thus well bang'd by theſe tools ſome will have them, and they muſt not be aboliſh't; pray let them be left indifferent; Let him that would have a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole, have one; and he that would have none, let him not be obliged to play with a poſt, a poſt that hath almoſt beaten out his brains.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59983:18"/>
            <p>Love can never flouriſh in the Church, if Impoſitions the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of contention and diviſions in it are continued. The heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings and Schiſms cauſed by them, are chargeable upon the impoſers, who will not ſuffer Chriſtians to enjoy the Ordinances upon the terms appointed by our Lord.
<q rend="margQuotes">Eccleſiaſtical Superiors are as much concerned to take heed of Schiſmatical Impoſitions,<note place="margin">Corbet, <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> Pag. 73.</note> as the people are to ſhun Schiſmatical recuſancy and diſobedience.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. They hinder love between Miniſters and the People. They beget a diſlike in the Miniſters of their Pariſhioners when they leave the publick Worſhip, and this diſlike grows to ſuch a ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards their Neighbours, that they loſe many opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of doing them good, which they might do by a free and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle correſpondence with them. They make the People to deſpiſe us when they ſee us to be fond of things which they know to be trifles. And how can they love us when they have no value for us? We live in a knowing age, people ſee the vanity of thoſe things on which ſome among us place all their zeal, they know that by the diviſions cauſed by them all our miſeries and dangers were let in upon us; and if we ſtill ſtickle for them they will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor us, believing that we do not care if we bring them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into all thoſe calamitous confuſions, from which we are ſo lately delivered. Let us not deceive our ſelves; the intereſt of the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> doth not depend on the continuance of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, we ſhall gain much more upon the People by caſting them away. They value us only for Piety, Sobriety and Diligence; and where there are ſuch as the Prophet deſcribes, they flock to the Aſſemblies of Diſſenters:<note place="margin">Iſa. 56, 10,
11, 12.</note> they value not their Conformity if they are Drones, or do not Preach ſeriouſly and profitably.</p>
            <p>Is it worth the while to continue the things that have driven multitudes from our Communion, and deprived us of many advantages of being uſeful for the good of their Souls? Let us lay aſide all ſtumbling blocks, and labour to the utmoſt of our power to promote ſound knowledge in all our ſeveral Stations; this will engage and fix the love of the People on us.
<q rend="margQuotes">When the publick order throughly promotes the means of ſound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">Corbet, <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> Pag. 164.</note> and encourageth real Godlineſs, it ſatisfies the minds of them who juſtly expect in a Goſpel Church and Miniſtry more than an outward Form, even the manifeſtation of Truth and Spiritual Light, Life and Power; and it prevents their wandring <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59983:18"/> to ſeek after it in the devious paths of Sectaries.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> III. They hinder Communion of Churches. We have ſtood at too great a diſtance from other Reformed Churches. Zeal for little things wherein we differ from them, hath made us too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to conſider and value their Intereſts, and hath been a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the moſt deſireable and advantageous correſpondence with them, for the advancement of the Goſpel in the World. When by the great deliverance from all the badges of our former ſlavery under Antichriſt, we are freed from all unneceſſary terms of Communion, all the Churches of Chriſt will be at liberty to conſult the common Intereſt of Reformed Chriſtianity for the welfare of the Myſtical Body of our Lord. The ſeveral diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of particular Churches may have applications, fit for them according to the advice of other Churches, which will be more impartial in their counſel, than perſons at home; and ſuch advice is ſometimes better received.</p>
            <p>Thus I have muſtered ſix Regiments of miſchiefs from our Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; many more might be drawn forth; but I think here is enough to give us a warm alarm, if we are not ſo far blinded as not to ſee the true Intereſt of Chriſtianity, and of Souls; and laid in ſuch a deep ſleep of carnal ſecurity, that nothing, will awaken us.</p>
            <p>Let me turn from the warm men to the Pious and Learned Paſtors of the Church.</p>
            <p>O my Reverend Fathers, and Brethren, <hi>The Chariots of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Horſemen thereof;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings
2.12.</note> it depends much on your pious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to calm the ſtorms that rage in ſome mens minds, to heal our breaches, and by a Union of all good Proteſtants to make us a terror to our Enemies. Let me ſpeak unto you in the words that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> put up unto God: <hi>Let not all the trouble ſeem little that hath come upon us, on our Kings, on our Princes, and on our Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 9.32.</note> 
               <hi>and on our Prophets, and on our Fathers, and on all the People</hi> of this Monarchy, ſince a furious Perſecution begun for Ceremonies, ſet all the three Kingdoms in a flame, watered the Fields with Blood, laid many Families and Houſes in ruine, and ended in the Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal death of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>The return of theſe inſtruments of miſchief with
<hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, ſet on foot another Perſecution which provoked God to fling us into the hands of a Popiſh Prince, who brought us ſo near <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59983:19"/>to deſtruction, that we were as a Sacrifice bound on the Altar, ready for the fatal ſtroke; and as the Apoſtle ſaid of his danger in a tempeſt, <hi>all hope that we ſhould be ſaved was then taken away.</hi> But God,<note place="margin">Acts 27.20.</note> (whoſe Infinite Wiſdom is never at a loſs to find a way of redemption in the greateſt extremity, and whoſe arm is never ſhortned that it ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not ſave) appeared for us when all help failed, <hi>he raiſed up the righteous man from the</hi> Eaſt, drove away our Enemies before him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 41.2.</note> as
<hi>Duſt and Stubble</hi> is driven away by a Whirl-wind. We for what we brought upon our ſelves, by our Zeal for little things, may be ſaid to have
<hi>ſold our ſelves for nought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">52.3.</note> yet God
<hi>Redeemed us without Money:</hi> Our reſcue from a Wilderneſs of Confuſion, and from the Houſe of Bondage, did not put us to the hundredth part of the charge that our controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Ceremonies have coſt us.<note place="margin">Ezra.
9.13, 14.</note> And now, <hi>after all that is come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us for</hi> our rigour towards tender Conſciences, <hi>ſeeing God hath puniſhed us leſs than our iniquities deſerve, and hath given us ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance as this: ſhould we again break his Commandments, and put any ſtumbling-block or occaſion to fall in our brothers way?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom.
14.13.</note> 
               <hi>Would not he be angry with us till he hath conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping?</hi> God who for us Commanded deliverance from the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> can give long wings to deſtruction from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> that it ſhall overtake us ſuddenly when we think leaſt of it. May not judgments hang over our heads, for the murmurings of ſome amongſt us, and the coldneſs of others towards the healing propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of Peace among Proteſtants? Is not <hi>Ireland</hi> all on fire? Are there not Enemies armed in <hi>Scotland?</hi> And tho they are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, may not God for our Sins increaſe their Power, and let them into <hi>England,</hi> to turn the point of his avenging Sword againſt our doors? He needs not winds to tranſport Executioners of his wrath, nor long Marches of Forces to bring Deſtruction upon us, he can raiſe up Enemies from among our ſelves, that ſhall do his ſtrange work effectually. If we conſider our want of bowels of compaſſion towards Souls driven from our Communion by Impoſitions, we have reaſon to wonder at the mercy of God in reſtraining the ſecret rage of all men round about us, that they do not in a furious fit cut us in pieces. What a tempeſtuous, unruly Sea is the wickedneſs of all mankind, and what a mighty power is it which binds up the rage of ſo many Devils in fleſh?<note place="margin">Eph.
2.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Devil worketh in the Children of Diſobedience.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59983:19"/>All men would be ſuch Children if Divine Grace did not make the difference: if it were not for ſome Principles in the Conſcience, and external impediments, all Nations would be mad. The whole Body of mankind is a great Regiment of <hi>French</hi> Dragoons. <hi>France</hi> in its preſent deſolations is a Paradiſe to what it would be, if God did not
<hi>reſtrain the remainder of wrath.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa.
70.10.</note> Inſtead of devouring Gods Lambs only, they would be Lions and Tygers to one another, filling that Country with Blood and Carcaſes. And that Kingdom in ſuch confuſions would be a Picture of what the whole World would be, if wickedneſs were every where let looſe. The Maſſacres and Cruelties of any age or place are not to be thought ſtrange: but it is a wonder that all times are not ſanguinary, and that all Countreys are not fill'd with Garments rouled in Blood. Dare we be hard towards our Brethren in a World full of furies, that can only be reſtrained by the Power of God, whom we provoke by offending the weak? The nearer we are to him in profeſſion, the more dreadful will his wrath be upon us for our Sins. How did his anger burn againſt <hi>Iſrael?</hi> He did let looſe Wild Beaſts of Prey to Worry his peculiar People, and to devour the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his Friend, ſuffered the <hi>Wild Boar to waſie the Vineyard which his right hand had planted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 80.13, 14, 15. Amos 3.2.</note> Judgment is ſwift and heavy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sinners in Sion. <hi>You only have I known of all the Families of the Earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi> He is more ſevere towards his own People for ſin, than others that know him not. When he viſits the World with his Judgments the firſt ſtrokes fall upon his Church. The Cup of his fury that was to go round all Nations, began at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 25.15,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> We who ſerve in the Sanctuary are more in danger of Plagues for our Male-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, than other men that are more remote. The men with ſlaughter-weapons in their hands were Commanded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the Sanctuary. God can provide ſlaughter-men and ſlaughter-weapons for us, if we will not be merciful to Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>He ſhall have judgment without mercy, that hath ſhewed no mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2.13. 1 Per. 4
17. Pſ. 79.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>The time is come that judgment muſt begin at the Houſe of God.</hi> How terrible hath this been in former times? <hi>The dead Bodies of thy Servants have they given to be meat to the Fouls of the Heaven, the Fleſh of thy Saints unto the Beaſts of the Earth. Their Blood have they ſhed like Water round about</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>If we would avoid all the Plagues that attend Oppreſſors and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59983:20"/>Perſecutors of Conſcience, we muſt caſt away all Impoſitions, and give the beſt incouragement to them who labour moſt to maintain the power of Godlineſs in themſelves and others.
<q rend="margQuotes">Thoſe who agree with us in all the Subſtantials of Religion, and add no dangerous or deſtructive Tenet to theſe,<note place="margin">Bolde <hi>of Perſecutior,</hi> Pag. 20.</note> who are holy, ſober chaſte temperate, righteous, compaſſionate and merciful, and who no way endeavour to diſturb the publick Peace, but are vigorous Proteſtants, and reſolute oppoſers of the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion, and Civil Rights, they ought (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidering our preſent circumſtances) to be ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſecuted and Oppreſſed, as to have all the incouragement and countenance that pious Chriſtians, and Loyal Subjects can claim and deſerve.</q> If you thus ſupport Piety, and relieve ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, you ſhall be bleſſed and honoured, and your flocks ſhall flouriſh under your conduct: Clergy and People ſhall be an ornament and ſtrength one to another. <hi>If you undo the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burdens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.6.</note> 
               <hi>and let the oppreſſed</hi> (grieved Conſciences) <hi>go free, and break every yoke of needleſs Impoſitions: Then ſhall your light break forth as the morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and the glory of the Lord ſhall be your rere-ward. He ſhall guide you continually, and ſatisfie your Souls. And you ſhall be called the repairers of the breach, and reſtorers of paths to dwell in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you chiefly mind the Glory of God and the good of ſouls, all your enemies ſhall fall into contempt, and God <hi>ſhall bring forth your Righteouſneſs as the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 37.6.</note> notwithſtanding all the obloquy caſt upon you by evil men. Your Enemies ſhall be like chaff driven away. They are but like the ſmall Particles of duſt which continually beat upon us, and are not felt nor diſcerned but in the Sun beams. Millions of theſe are continually agitated about us by the Air in motion; The moſt enraged Enemies of our Church are but breathing duſt moved by the breath of Life, which is <hi>but a vapour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jan. 4.14.</note> The whole rabble of Antichriſtian furies now in combination againſt us in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> are but Gods Priſoners in Chains; if he ſuffer them to rattle their fetters about the ears of the faithful, yet they ſhall never be able wholly to deſtroy them: <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ma. 16.18.</note> The head of the Church, is the Judge of the World, he will not ſuffer his Jail-birds to triumph over his Body.</p>
            <p>I have done with the fourth conſideration, the manifold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59983:20"/>of theſe Impoſitions. I have been long wading through them; but the grief of innumerable tender conſciences under the weight of them, hath been longer and very deplorable. Length here cannot be avoided: theſe little things have cauſed ſo many miſchiefs, that it is very difficult to ſpeak little of them. I ſhall now proceed to the laſt conſideration and conclude.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> V. The danger that threatens us in the continuance of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the Worſhip of God. It is hoped that they who do not ſeriouſly conſider the diſtreſs of others, may be awakened with the black proſpect of their own danger. We are threatned with a double danger, preſent and future.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Our preſent danger. This may be ſet forth in three Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The continuance of theſe things will bring upon us the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and hatred of the People. Multitudes in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey have a Prejudice againſt us for the late miſcarriages of ſome, and the unſeaſonable ſtiffneſs of others for the things that divide and weaken us, when it concerns us all to be united as one man againſt the common Enemy. If this temper ſhould prevail, we ſhall be abhorred by all men, for expoſing the publick happineſs to the danger of Ruin, only for things of no value, and which we acknowledge to be in their own nature Indifferent.<note place="margin">Bolde. <hi>Plea for Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Pag. 5.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">It is high high time to leave off inſiſting on little Punctilio's of Honour; we ought duly to weigh our circumſtances, and the nature of the things we contend about, and if our dangers be unmeaſurably great, and the things we differ about ſuch as will not bear ſo great a weight, as the loſs of our Religion and all our Rights, we muſt yield ſomething on either ſide, and that ſide muſt be willing to part with moſt, that can do it with greateſt eaſe, and moſt innocence.</q> The Diſſenters doubt of the Lawfulneſs of ſome of our terms of Communion, and therefore cannot yield to us; but we may with eaſe and innocence condeſcend to them in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Impoſitions not appointed by God.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Small differences muſt give place to the greater Points,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, <hi>Pag. 11.</hi>
                  </note> in which we are at one; for all that act otherwiſe ſhew clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that tho they do not think it decent to ſpeak out what they think, yet in their hearts they undervalue the Common Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion in which we agree; but ſet a real va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon indifferent matters, and are acted by the heats and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59983:21"/> of a Party, to which all other things give place.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Our Brethren have according to the Act of Indulgence ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed our Doctrine, and thereby are incorporated into the Church of
<hi>England.</hi> The People ſee by this, that they agree with us in the Subſtantials of our Religion, and they may account us guilty of Peev iſhneſs and Malice if we continue thoſe little things as terms of Communion which we know they cannot comply with. And to do this after our acknowledgements in diſtreſs, and a promiſe of coming to a due temper may make them abhor us as Enemies to our Countrey.
<q rend="margQuotes">Tho ſome of our make-bats, who do whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imploy their Talents to widen our differences,<note place="margin">Bolde
<hi>Plea for Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> pag. 6.</note> do pretend to the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> I am verily perſwaded they are either Real Papiſts, or very miſchievous Inſtruments in Popiſh hands, to effect and bring about the common Ruin of Proteſtants.</q> It cannot be with a good deſign, that at this time of day, they are Zealous for things that they know will continue a great diviſion amongſt us. It is not to be doubted, but that the croſsneſs and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Practices of ſome Clergy-men and Prieſt-ridden Gentlemen: have obſtructed affairs in Parliament, hindred the relief of
<hi>Derry</hi> to the loſs of many Thouſand Gallant men: <hi>Ireland</hi> had been in a fair way of recovery, and the Rebellion in <hi>Scotland</hi> had not come to ſuch a head but for ſuch tools. Some of our Guides are more unkind to <hi>England</hi> than Forreigners. The <hi>Dutch</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe our liberty, beſides the charge of 600000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> ventured a great fleet and a conſiderable Army, when they might have wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it themſelves: but ſome among us will not part with a few trifles to ſave Church and State. Will not ſuch folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs bring upon us the contempt and hatred of all men, and make the wiſe and the good aſhamed to own us? The Clergy counting them to be 20000 (which is much too large a reckoning, there not being 10000 Pariſhes in <hi>England</hi>) are but the
250th part of the Nation, ſuppoſing the People to be but 5 Millions: and ſhall 249 ſouls be expoſed to all kind of dangers and miſeries for the mad humour of one man? All the pious, ſober and moderate Clergy-men are for a Union: the reſt are ſome of them Dignified Drones, theſe fear contempt if more diligent labourers are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church; ſome are learned, but are inflamed with a Phariſaical Zeal for the form of Godlineſs, denying the Power thereof; ſome are debauched, and fear the ſevere correction
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59983:21"/>that is due unto them; Some are departed from our Doctrine, and fear (here the ſhoe pincheth) that their errors will be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the acceſſion of ſuch an Orthodox Intereſt as the Body of the Presbyterians who are firm to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Some are ſo ſottiſh, that they act their part very ill, and would be undone if their tools were taken away: all our ſticklers, are Tantivees for their own humours, and care not what becomes of our Religion, Laws and Liberties. Many of theſe are the Diſciples of Old <hi>Roger,</hi> helped to cry him up, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him as a great Pillar of the Church: with him they Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Invaſions that were made upon our Rights, and the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous executions of Proteſtant Noblemen and Gentlemen in the late times of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ery and Arbitrary Popery.</p>
            <p>If the Sword ſhould be drawn again in <hi>England,</hi> how ſeverely will this unmercifulneſs of Clergy-men be revenged upon them, as the cauſe of all our miſeries, by their perverſeneſs for toys? Such troublers of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> may expect nothing leſs than a total extirpation, and that the people will make ſure work with a ſort of men, that are not content to have once imbroiled the three Kingdoms in a bloody War for indifferent things, but do now take the ſame methods for the ſame vanities to make us paſs through all thoſe calamities again.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. Our danger of loſing all our lately recovered Rights, if by our diviſions we ſhould again let in the common enemy. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is a Plot and Conſpiracy againſt all the Intereſts of mankind, ſtrikes at the foundations of humane Society, and will not ſuffer men to uſe their reaſon and ſenſes, depoſeth &amp; aſſaſſinates Kings, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, Subjects from their Allegiance &amp; Diſpenſeth with the moſt horrid wickedneſſes. It is a Religion that loves to lap in humane blood, and hath filled the World with Slaughters.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Moor <hi>Divine Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lognes.</hi> pag. 161.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Pope <hi>Julius</hi> in ſeven years was the occaſion of the Slaughter of 200000 Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The Maſſacre in
<hi>France</hi> in three months cut off a 100000. P. <hi>Perionius</hi> avers that in the Perſecution of the <hi>Albingenſes</hi> and
<hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes</hi> 1000000 loſt their lives. From the beginning of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits till 1580 that is, thirty or forty years, 900000 periſhed, ſaith
<hi>Balduinus,</hi>
               </q> The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> by the hangman put to death
36000. <hi>Vergerius</hi> affirms that the Inquiſition in 30 years deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 150000. To all this I may add the Iriſh Rebellion in which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59983:22"/>were deſtroyed 300000, as the Lord <hi>Orery</hi> reports in a Paper print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> II.</p>
            <p>Tho ſome new-faſhioned Divines have repreſented Popery in favourable Colours, and endeavoured to clear the Pope from the old charge of being Antichriſt; for the baffling of ſuch flattering Doctors, comes the late (and I hope the laſt perſecution from Antichriſt) Dragon Perſecution in <hi>France, Orange</hi> and <hi>Savoy.</hi> This hath out-done all Perſecutions both Pagan and Papal that ever were in the World. No Perſecution, no nor all the perſecutions together contained in them all the barbarities of this. Never any raged to ſuch a high degree of ſubtilty, malice and cruelty; in this have ſuffered above 150000, who would heartily have choſen to change a miſerable life for death: but life was c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>inued; to load it with longer miſeries, and death was denied, as a favour too great for them. Innumerable were the violences that were committed on the Souls, Bodies, and Eſtates of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>They grieved the modeſt Souls of vertuous Women and Maids by hanging them up naked by their feet, or by their arm-pits, thus expoſing them to publick view. In Parents they tormented their bowels of natural affection: They bound mothers (that gave ſuck) unto poſts, and let their infants lye in their ſight ſeveral days, languiſhing, Crying, Moaning, Gaſping for Life; and even dying for Hunger and Thirſt, Swearing to them they ſhould not give Suck till they abjured. The new art of waging War againſt the reaſon of Chriſtians is a Deviliſm never practiſed before: they poured Wine down their throats till the fumes overcame their reaſon; to deſtroy their reaſon for want of ſleep, they Tickled, Laſhed, Flung them about, threw buckets of water on their faces, made a continual noiſe upon kettles over their heads and torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them a 1000 ways. By this many were diſtracted, and others became mopiſh and ſtupid.</p>
            <p>All the tragical methods of that perſecution, had before this been acted again in <hi>England;</hi> if God had not in mercy ſent our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign to <hi>ſave us from the Lyons mouth.</hi> Let us remember and conſider what hath been done upon others, and let their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings be a warning to us, that we give no advantage to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by continuing any of the inſtruments that divided and weakened us, brought upon us our late confuſions and ſtill <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59983:22"/>threaten us with danger. A relapſe would be a greater evil, than any we have yet had a proſpect of: The cruelty of Popery againſt Hereticks would be raiſed to a higher degree than ever, by an infatiable thirſt of revenge upon us for our inſolency in throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off our Fetters and Chains. All that hath been acted under Paganiſm and Popery, will be unſpeakably ſhort of what we muſt feel, if we return again to the houſe of Bondage. Our task will be doubled and trebled, the Fiery Furnace ſhall be heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeven times hotter than ever, and ſeventy times too if they can do it.</p>
            <p>If after all that we have ſeen and feared, and others have ſadly felt, any amongſt us reſolve ſtill to ſtickle for their Toys, it may be ſaid of them as of the <hi>Caldeans:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer.
50.38.</note> 
               <hi>They are mad upon their Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> III. Our danger in reſpect of Gods Judgments which we may bring upon our heads. Tho Popery ſhould never be able to lift up its head again in this Land; yet if we continue in the ſame courſe that provoked God to caſt us into the late confuſions, he can find other plagues to inflict upon us. We know not a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier plague than Popery, but he can ſend one that ſhall be more terrible and deſtructive. In his Word he ſpeaks mildly to rigorous Governours: <hi>What mean ye that beat my people to pieces?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3.15,</note> But he will thunder in his Judgments againſt them that break his flock to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſcattering them from the Communion of his Church by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary impoſitions.</p>
            <p>Tho by the Act of Indulgence the inſtruments of Perſecution are ſtruck out of the hands of Perſecutors, yet we may be ſtill guilty of Perſecution, if we continue thoſe things that armed evil men againſt his people, and do ſtill drive his Lambs from their Paſtures, and the puniſhment of perſecution may overtake us.
<q rend="margQuotes">The black-horſes, the inſtruments of the execution of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">Charnock <hi>Vol.</hi> 2.
<hi>on</hi> Exod. 15.9, 10. pag. 50.</note> were ſent towards
<hi>Babylon,</hi> where his people were in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, <hi>Zech.</hi> 6.6.</q> Their's was only a bodily Captivity, their conſciences were free. Are not Gods people now in Spiritual Captivity, when they muſt not enjoy his Ordinances with us, but upon terms they cannot conform to and he never appointed? Have not we reaſon to expect that the black horſes ſhould be let looſe to run ſwiftly and furiouſly upon us? By endeavouring to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59983:23"/>continue our ſtubble we may be oppoſers of God in the great work that he ſeems to be doing for his Church: the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to a purer and more glorious State. It may be obſerved that generally a glorious ſtate in the Church hath followed her greateſt ſtraits. In
<hi>Egypt</hi> when the task was doubled and ſtraw denyed,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſent, and God delivered his people by ſigns, and wonders, and great terrours. The Jews were without Urim and Thummin, without the Spirit of Propheſy, when Chriſt came in the fleſh to work Redemption. How low was the infant Church when Chriſt was in the Grave, his diſciples all ſcattered? How black the hour, and great the Power of Darkneſs, when the Sun was darkened and the earth trembled? This was followed with the accompliſhment of the great Prophecy that <hi>Japhet</hi> ſhould dwell in the Tents of <hi>Sem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 9.27.</note> delivered by <hi>Noah</hi> about two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years before, fulfilled in the raiſing of a Gentile Church. The Church was more glorious after the Pariſian Maſſacre, the perſecution in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and the
<hi>Marian</hi> Flames in <hi>England. Hamans</hi> Plot to deſtroy all the Jews, cauſed great mourning, and Faſting,<note place="margin">Eſth.
4.3.8.16.</note> and Weeping amongſt them: But the plotter is hanged on his own Gallows; and the Jews had Light, and Joy and honour. We have reaſon to hope, that after the late Plot for the Extirpation of the Northern Hereſie, and the great Extremity this Church was reduced to, ſhe ſhall now be more beautiful and glorious than ever, if the peeviſhneſs of ſome doth not cauſe a delay of this happineſs.
<q rend="margQuotes">The ſharpeſt pangs precede delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; it was ſo when Chriſt came in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Charnock, <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>on</hi> Exod. 15.9, 10. pag.
46.</note> it will be ſo at every new riſing of Chriſt in the Spirit.</q> If people did look before them, and conſider the Providence of God, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of things, they would be more indifferent towards Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things; the Divine Power and Jealouſie would cool their blind Zeal for ſuch matters, they would be afraid to oppoſe his work, leſt he ſend upon them that Woe that is denounced againſt them that preſume to <hi>ſtrive with their Maker.</hi> It is a dangerous thing to be found fighters againſt God.<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.9.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Gods Counſel muſt ſtand,<note place="margin">Fulfilling of Scripture <hi>Part. 3.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Popery, <hi>p. ult.</hi>
                  </note> Oh! At what a rate do theſe now run in the way of his wrath and vengeance, and to be partakers of the ſame plagues with Antichriſt, who yet will not ceaſe, for giving <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59983:23"/> their power to ſupport that accurſed and falling intereſt!</q> This is not at all to be accounted ſtrange, that men ſhould walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, and oppoſe him; there were always ſuch as did ſet themſelves againſt his work in the World, and there are now Children of <hi>Belial</hi> (all zealous for Ceremonies to a man) that murmur againſt their own happineſs beſtowed upon them by God in bringing about the moſt wonderful revolution that ever was. We have the leſs reaſon to admire this ſtubbornneſs in man, becauſe the Devil, a ſubtle Spirit, and knows that his oppoſing God will increaſe his future miſery,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et he is ſo blinded with malice that he always wageth War againſt his Creator and Judge.<note place="margin">Charnock, <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>on</hi> Pſ. 87.5. p. 26.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">It is an aſtoniſhment, that the Devil after ſo long an experience ſhould be ſuch a fool as to engage in new attempts when he hath found ſo little Succeſs in the former, and hath had ſo many ages to witneſs the baffles he hath received; what a fool is he to think that the defender of the Church ſhould be conquered by a revolted angel, that lies under an everlaſting curſe?</q> This ſhould make us all to ſuſpect our ſelves, when we are warm for things that are not appointed by God, and are ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks to many pious Chriſtians: It is much better to fear to offend the weak, than to run raſhly on, leſt we be found to walk contrary unto God, and provoke him to walk contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. He hath many plagues for them that do ſo: After many Judgments,<note place="margin">Lev. 26.18</note> he tells the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that he
<hi>will puniſh them ſeven times more for their ſins.</hi> And if they ſtill <hi>walk contrary unto him,</hi> he ſaith again: <hi>I will bring ſeven times more Plagues upon you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21.</note>
               <hi>according to your ſins.</hi> The like alſo, <hi>v.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">27.</note> And if yet they <hi>walk contrary unto him:</hi> he ſaith: <hi>I will walk contrary unto you in fury; and I, even I,</hi>
               <note place="margin">28.</note> 
               <hi>will chaſtiſe you ſeven times for your ſins.</hi> Here are 28 degrees of puniſhment which number he can mount much higher for the Chaſtiſement of them, who after manifold experience of our Confuſions and miſeries occaſioned by quarrels about trifles, will yet for them walk contrary unto him. There have been innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Judgments executed in the world, and Judgments recorded in the Word of God, and there are alſo unwritten plagues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for his obſtinate enemies: <hi>Every Sickneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.61.</note> 
               <hi>and every Plague which is not written in the Book of this Law, them will the Lord bring upon thee, until thou be deſtroyed.</hi> But if after many methods of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59983:24"/>people will continue perverſe,<note place="margin">Ezek.
38.18. Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3. Am. 4.11,
12.</note> 
               <hi>his fury ſhall come up in his face; he will take vengeance, and will not meet them as a man,</hi> but as a God. <hi>Yet ye have not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord. Therefore thus will I do unto</hi> Iſrael: <hi>and becauſe I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> II. Our future danger from the continuance of Ceremonies, and that in reſpect of the account we muſt give to our Judge. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Plenty and Eaſe may harden the hearts of ſome of us againſt tenderly conſidering the danger of Souls excluded from our Communion, and thereby expoſed as a prey to Sectaries: but all the glory and pleaſure of this world will be contemptible when <hi>the ſign of the Son of man ſhall appear in heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24 30. Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 26.13.</note> His glory at
<hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> was unto <hi>Paul a light from heaven above the brightneſs of the Sun.</hi> That ſign may be ſuch a glory filling the whole World with the brightneſs thereof, every where ſeen by amazed mankind. He who hath created the glorious body of the Sun, which is 139 (ſome ſay 166) times bigger than this Globe in which we live, can ſpread a more Glorious Light over this point of earth or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of duſt, for ſo it is if compared with the vaſt extent of the Heavens. Whatever that ſign ſhall be, it is like it ſhall be viſible to all, not only to the righteous for their comfort, but alſo to the wicked for their terrour.<note place="margin">Mat.
24.30. Gen. 49.5.</note> It is ſaid that <hi>all the tribes of the Earth ſhall then mourn.</hi> They of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> who are for
<hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Cruelty</hi> ſhall have their ſhare in the mourning. What trembling will ſeize upon them,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.16,
17.</note> when the mighty blaſt of Gods Trumpet ſhall awake all the Sleepers in the duſt, them that have not lodged ſix days in the Grave,<note place="margin">1 Cor 15.52.</note> and the Sleepers of 6000 years. His power ſhall raiſe all the dead, and change the living <hi>in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the twinkling of an Eye.</hi> An univerſal flame ſhall embrace the heavens and the earth (the God of our proud and covetous Formaliſts,) melt the frozen World in the <hi>Laodicean</hi> State.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10.</note>
               <hi>The Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 20.12.</note> 
               <hi>The dead ſmall and great ſhall ſtand before God to be judged according to their works.</hi> Then mocking <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> that have ſcoffed at the pure in heart as Puritans, Preciſe Fools, and Melancholy dull Souls; ſhall take the Fools cap unto themſelves,
<q rend="margQuotes">and they repenting,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> and groaning for anguiſh of Spirit, ſhall ſay <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59983:24"/>within themſelves, This was he whom we had ſometimes in deriſion, and a proverb of reproach. We fools accounted his life madneſs; and his end to be without honour. How is he numbred among the Children of God, and his Lot is among the Saints!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Some among us are angry with <hi>Calvin</hi> for calling humane rites <hi>tolerables ineptias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glis</hi> Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. p. 98.</note> They will not at the great day be ſuch unto rigorous Impoſers, who made them terms of Communion. How will you at that day lift up your faces before your Maſter and your Judge, when he ſhall demand of you, What is become of thoſe his Lambs which you drove into the Wilderneſs by needleſs Impoſitions? He requires you to pray unto the Lord of the harveſt, that he would fend forth more labourers into his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and you keep away many worthy labourers from his work, becauſe they cannot comply with terms that he never appointed. We may think it a light matter to offend weak Chriſtians, but it will not be always ſo: <hi>Wo unto the World becauſe of offences:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>For it muſt needs be that offences come: but wo unto that man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> Offences will hereafter be as heavy to the Impoſers of humane inventions, as they are now to the weak. The puniſhment of them that offend one of Chriſts little ones will be more dreadful than being caſt into the Sea with a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone about the neck.<note place="margin">Luk. 17.2.</note> If, Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels, ſhall be the lighteſt puniſhment inflicted on them that feed not the hungry, and do not cloath the naked; how deep will their lodging be in the lake of Fire and Brimſtone, who lay Stumbling-blocks before multitudes of Souls to their ſo great Scandal, that they forſake the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt? how terrible will it be to be <hi>puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.9.</note>
               <hi>from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power?</hi> This will be heavier than many Milſtones: For all the works and Mountains in the world will be light in compariſon of the weight of the wrath of the Lamb. The ravening Wolves that have worried Chriſts Flock, the great Clerks that have troubled Church and State with their ſtiffneſs for very little things, the mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> that have deſolated the earth, ſhall in vain cry for a covering to the frighted and flying Mountains, and the molten Rocks, that could not <pb n="44" facs="tcp:59983:25"/>ſave themſelves from the power of the Judge,
<hi>who made the Heaven to depart as a ſcroll when it is rolled together.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>And the Kings of the Earth; and the great men, and the rich men, and the chief Captains,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hid themſelves in the Dens and in the Rocks of the Mountains; and ſaid to the Mountains and Rocks, Fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
